<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Henry Ayres Blog</title>
    <description>A blog about sporting activities, life experiences and professional musings of Henry Ayres.
 Recently someone told me I should write a book of my experiences.  Perhaps this is the precursor to that?
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 08:08:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 08:08:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Better broadband throughout your home</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A conversation sprung up via a whats app group today caused by the news that finally we may get fiber to the cabernet and thus better broad band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the crux of the conversation was not about the speed of the Broadband to the house, it was about how much juice it loses between the router and the device in the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my old home, a 3 bed 1930’s council built semi in the middle of rural Oxfordshire we had little problem with the wifi signal at the farthest point away in the house.
I guess it help that during the refurbishment back in 2001 of all the downstairs walls I ran cat5 cable to convenient points, like behind the TV.
Then, after extending into the loft and moving the router up there I replaced it with a pretty powerful SOHO (Small Office Home Office) model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend was having trouble with there BT router and there BT sport/TV box.  The two were one room apart.
It is true that the wireless router actually gave up the ghost and had to be replaced but even then it was not sufficiently powerful for decent viewing.
However luck would have it that they already had a piece of cat5 neatly ran from the router to the back of the TV.   So it was an easy task to buy a terminator from Screwfix,
connect up to the cat5 and plug in.  Bingo.  A perfect picture and hours of premiership rugby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is the thing.  There is something about the houses in this neck of the woods.  They are like living in a Faraday cage.
Mobile phone signals don’t stand a chance and the same applies for wifi.
The room with the TV in is next to my office with the Wifi router but if you do not have the router in the optimal position, no Iplayer, no Amazon prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wifi is not that stable. Packets get lost so watching movies over it can be a poor experience if it gets really bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried an extender.  It works quite well.   The idea is plug it in the wall in between the black spot and wifi router and it will extend the the signal into the black spot.
I don’t see it as the final solution though. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00NIUHAG6/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o07_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wifi Extender&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to get the best out of the expensive broadband being pumped into your house then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buy the right type of business broad band.  You get a less contested line, so less people are using the cable from cabinet to exchange. My current deal is £35 (inc. vat),
 unlimited broad band, unlimited local and national calls and pretty cheap international.  I get 8Mgbs where all my neighbours get nowhere near.  In fact half.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buy an aftermarket SOHO modem wireless router.  They are more expensive but they have much more powerful wifi.  More often than not have 2 or 3 ariels that allow you to direct the wifi signal in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go for cat5 cable.  But you don’t want it hanging around in the house, right.  Well that’s fine; how many of you have cables neatly run around the outside of your house to carry phone, tv ariel, satellite cables.
You can buy armoured or waterproof cat5.  A couple of neat holes and you can get true broad band from your router to the device i.e. the TV.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cablemonkey.co.uk/cat5e-rj45-patch-leads/9587-external-cat5e-utp-ldpe-rj45-patch-leads.html?ipa=2897&amp;amp;gclid=CLXsmpDHi9ICFWUz0wod4zAJNg#/34-length-10m&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Example of waterproof patch cable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/02/12/better-broad-band-in-your-house.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/02/12/better-broad-band-in-your-house.html</guid>
        
        <category>general</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>broadband</category>
        
        <category>networking</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 27 - Southern Ocean Duel.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After this weeks amazing Southern Ocean video footage and lead swapping between &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vendeeglobe.org/en/skippers/55/armel-le-cleac-h&quot;&gt;Armel Le Cléac’h&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt; Hugo Boss here is my take on what is going on deep in the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video footage from the French Navy Helicopter was exceptional.  As a sailing fan we have never really seen this sort of deep Southern ocean footage.
And more interestingly it told a story of this race.   Le Cleac’h video appeared first in it we see the boat powering along at a steady and good pace on port tack.
At this point Le Cleac’h was ahead of Thomson.  The boat is generally flat and the skipper took no risks of getting wet and barely came out from under the extended 
cuddy these boats now sport to keep the excessive water off.  He has a fractional reacher and 2 reefs in the main. 
The boat looked stable as it used the full possibilities of its undamaged foils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut to Hugo Boss. Alex tells the helicopter his sail plan but you can see it as well.  Two reefs, fractional code zero &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; a stay-sail.
Alex comes bouncing out of the boat like an excited puppy, using the opportunity of going outside to tidy up and check a few things, iterally running all
over the boat.  He finishes off by standing on the weather rail proudly holding a Union Jack.   The boat, without its starboard foil is bucking and literally
ploughing its way through the waves (you can see why autopilot failure at these extremes are so catastrophic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then the lead has swapped several times.  On port tack, if the wind is up, say 30kts, then advantage Thomson as he fearlessly loads up the sails and ploughs on.
It is becoming apparent at this wind speed and sea state that the foils add less help.  Don’t forget, this is the first time foils have been used in the
southern ocean and certainly the first time they have raced with them.  If the wind moderates to below 25 or even 20kts, advantage Le Cleac’h as the foils begin to
lift the boat out of the water and the stump Thomson is left with just holds him back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the case untill they to gybe Starboard.  At this point Thomson appears to be faster in al point of sail off the wind and closes any lead that has opened
and then opens up a lead of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after tacking downwind, bouncing off the ice gate for the last few days, I believe according to Thomson’s 
latest update they are now on port and will stay there for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets hope he can start to really build a lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That statement might appear a bit jingoistic, but hey this is my blog and I am a Brit, 
but there are many others in the sailing world who would like an English speaking win of this famously French race.
If Thomson wins then it is almost certain that a Short Handed Offshore Keelboat race would enter the olympics within the next few cycles.
This at the recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yachtracingforum.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yacht Racing Forum&lt;/a&gt; was proposed by many as the saviour of olympic sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if it is but it would be a hell of a lot of fun.  And perhaps my Olympic dream might not be over yet!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news in the race Jean-Pierre Dick on St Michael Virbac has had to do an interesting about turn to avoid a penalty being imposed after he 
strayed over the virtual ice wall (see below video).  He did not download the most recent update (it moves depending on Ice reports) and was force to retrace his steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This race continues to deliver vast quantities of excitement.  Imagine it all on TV with an Olympic Gold at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9KUQdbWUCgY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday27-0400.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 27 0400UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 27 0400UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/12/04/vendee-southern-ocean-dual.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/12/04/vendee-southern-ocean-dual.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 22 - A close race.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt; Hugo Boss has slipped into second after a day of sailing on a more close
hauled course along the virtual ice wall.  With the boats still on port tack and quite close to the wind Boss has been struggling with its broken foil.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vendeeglobe.org/en/skippers/55/armel-le-cleac-h&quot;&gt;Armel Le Cléac’h&lt;/a&gt; has eked out a 30 mile lead but as the Ice Wall retreats south
and the wind clocks round toward the west north west Thomson is holding the deficit at just that distance as the wind starts to build and
broaden the point of sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two sailors are turning this into a boat on boat battle; however, the rest of the fleet has dropped behind a serious of weather systems.
The nearest sailor is Seb Josse and he is already nearly 500nm off the pace.I expect if the wind moves nough for them to gybe then Thomson’s unbroken foil will then come into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking of which.  There has been quite a few comments wobbling round the internet that Thomson has a spare starboard foil onboard.
This was pretty much put to bed today by Alex in an interview with salinganarchy  where he states it would be 2 heavy, to cumbersome and too dificult 
to replace. Believe what you will!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday22-2100.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 22 21UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 22 2100UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/28/vendee-working-south.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/28/vendee-working-south.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 20 - Match Race.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On the brink of week 4 and after having the same leader for the past few weeks
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt; briefly allowed
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vendeeglobe.org/en/skippers/55/armel-le-cleac-h&quot;&gt;Armel Le Cléac’h&lt;/a&gt; into the lead before stealing it straight back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With his lead of 100nm being gradually eaten away by Le Cléac’h Thomson has been waiting in the lighter
winds to gybe onto starboard so he can get his intact port foil working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two boats are now engaged in a close match race as they enter the Indian Ocean and week 4 of the Vendee Globe.  Down at 42°
they have for the first time been slowed by light winds.  This is the roaring forties and the usually this would be where the sleigh
ride of to Cap Horn would start. After Thomson and the front of the fleet have smashed every every record
getting down the Atlantic with a new reference time to the Longitude of the Cape of Good Hope they have come to a 
pretty sharp halt as they have sailed into a area of unusually light winds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed in a previous post they would have, in past years, dived south in search of wind but the virtual Ice Wall (red dotted line 
in image below) stops them.
So the only way they can go is north but there is no wind there.  They are still sailing downwind but are going to suffer light and variable
winds for the next day or so as they wait for the low that Sebastien Josse is currently riding to catch them up.
Daily runs have dropped from 450+ to 258 for Thomson. This will give Josse a chance to close the 300 mile gap that has opened
up.  The rest of the fleet are way behind this still with 4th place SMA 830nm behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly some news outlets are reporting that Thomson has a new Starboard foil onboard and is just waiting for the
right moment to remove the stump and replace it with the new one.  It has also been pointed out by some that there has been
no pictures of the broken foil. They are suggestion that the skipper of Hugo Boss is being economical with the truth about how damaged it is.
This would be no surprise as while the sailors will go to hell and back to help a competitor in need, whilst the race is on a 
little sportsmanship is par for the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday20-0400.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 20 0400UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 20 0400UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/27/vendee-globe-match-race.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/27/vendee-globe-match-race.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 16 - Hugo Boss, broken but still fast.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We waited until nearly week 3 for the first casualty in the front runners but now they are coming thick and fast.
Vincent Rou aboard PRB who was managing to keep his previous generation boat in touch with the front pack hit a UFO
on Sunday and today has had to retire from the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first he thought he was going to be able to continue but over the following 24 hours it became apparent that his keel pivot
bearings had sustained damage and an irreversible deterioration of the mounting point had begun.  He is currently safe but on
route to Cape Town to effect repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt;  Hugo Boss was retaining the race lead by a distance of 90nm.
He has in fact manage to increase his lead after the collision that broke his foil.  However his course is sagging south toward the
ice exclusion zone.  He really needs to be able to gybe onto starboard and start to use his port foil but these wind condition 
will not let him for a few more days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter though. He is due at the longitude of The Cape of Good Hope before Friday which will set a new 
record and probably be as much as 4 days ahead of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the overall race the front 3 (now PRB has retired) have broken away into the next weather system and the fourth placed sailor,
Morgan Lagraviere, is already 280 miles astern of Thomson, sailing in a different direction and 5kts slower than the 3 leaders.
A full 3359 nautical miles covers the entire fleet not including Tanguy De Lamotte who is currently sailing back toward the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday morning the fantastic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seahorsemagazine.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Seahorse Magazine&lt;/a&gt;  landed on my door mat. 
In it was an article telling the story of the fantastic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yves_Parlier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yves Parlier&lt;/a&gt;. 
In the 2000/2001 edition of the race, his third, he was getting back on par with the leaders when he suffered an accidental 
gybe when his auto-helm failed, which resulted in the mast breaking in 3 places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was pretty critical deep in the southern ocean. In fact Eleen McArthur, en-route to second place, was temporarily
routed by the race organisers to provide assistance. However Parlier was not done with the race. 
Managing to fashion a jury rig he sailed north to Stuart Island, still at 47° South where he anchored. 
The organisers of the Vendee Globe allowed him to go ashore as long as he did not go above the high water line.
Here he fashioned a replacement mast by using the 3 pieces he had saved and glued them back together and baked them in a make shift oven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And off he set again toward the finish but his problems where not over.  He ran out of food and would ration himself to 800 calories a day.
Eventually he managed to catch some fish and on 16th March 2001 he crossed the finish line at Les Sables d’Olonne. 
A time of 126 Days 23 hours and 36 minutes.  Two other competitors were still to finish.  And Sailing Folklore was written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday16-2100.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 16 2100UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 16 2100UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/22/vendee-globe-hugo-boss-still-fast.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/22/vendee-globe-hugo-boss-still-fast.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The unofficial home of Bonnie Tyler Jokes.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The blog post I always wanted to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve just ordered Bonnie Tyler’s Goalkeeping Blunders Vol 2. &lt;br /&gt;
It’s just totally clips of Joe Hart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bumped into Bonnie Tyler in that London.  She said shall we go for a coffee?&lt;br /&gt;
I said Starbucks?  She said no.&lt;br /&gt;
I said Costa?  She said no.&lt;br /&gt;
I think she was holding out for a nero!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a Bonnie Tyler sat nav&lt;br /&gt;
It’s rubbish&lt;br /&gt;
It keeps telling me to turn around, then every now and then it falls apart!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came home from work one day and there was a blond haired woman tiling my kitchen singing her heart out&lt;br /&gt;
Ah I thought, that’s a Bonnie Tyler!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 19:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/jokes/2016/11/20/bonnie-tyler-jokes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/jokes/2016/11/20/bonnie-tyler-jokes.html</guid>
        
        <category>bonnie tyler</category>
        
        <category>jokes</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>jokes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 14 - The war of attrition starts.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So far in this Vendee Globe there has been relatively few broken boats in the first two weeks.
A welcome hiatus that has changed for the worse today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last Vendee (2013) 4 yachts retired in the first week alone with 3 being dismasted and one suffering a cracked hull.
So far in this edition one has returned to port and restarted and one has not retired yet but is sailing back toward
Les Sables-d’Olonne with a broken masthead where they will retire.  There has been few incidents on the yachts as well
apart from a few crunched ribs and banged heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all changed yesterday when Bertrand de Broc on MACSF retired after diving on his hull to see what damage had
been caused in a collision off the Portuguese .  It is reported that a large delaminated piece of material was hanging from his
hull causing vibration and a noise so loud that he could still hear it through noise canceling headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also yesterday British Race favourite &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt; luck ran out when he hit something in the
water that has destroyed his starboard foil. The scheds over the next few hours showed him lose a 50nm chunk of the lead he had ground out
over the past couple of days.  Currently he is retaining the lead. Just.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you that watched the video I posted the other day where Hugo Boss engineering director
Ross Daniel talked about the foils you may remember he suggested that the boat would lose only a small
percentage of speed if it lost its foils.  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/15/vendee-globe-its-not-what-the-forecast-said.html&quot;&gt;Its Not What the Forecast Said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that it still has the port one and it is expected that most of the sailing across the southern ocean will be on starboard tack.
But Don’t take my word for it, lets hear it from the horses mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WHmueg44Fis&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other yachting news Land Rover BAR have won the entire LV challenger series.  This, I think, means they take a point into the AC knockout
next year.  I will check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday14-1700.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 14 1700UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 14 1700UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/20/vendee-globe-the-war-of-attrition-starts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/20/vendee-globe-the-war-of-attrition-starts.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 13 - Deep into the south.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The leading boats in the Vendee Globe are now diving south at high speed riding a low pressure system off the Brazilian coast.
The sailors that are in the front pack will be routing themselves to stay on the front/northside of this low pressure and ride across the South Atlantic above the Ice Wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sailors cannot sail into as higher latitude as they feel like.  The constant threat of drifting ice from Antarctica means that the Vendee Globe organizers
position a virtual ice wall that starts at Gough Island (10° West, 40° North) which the sailors leave that to starboard and continues on around the world 
to prevent them from getting to near the Antarctic ice.    The sailors will then slip away south toward the Kerguelen Islands before staying within
1500 miles of the south coast of Australia, so 1500 miles from a rescue center before the wall bends away again down to 60° for the passing of Cape Horn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 1996 race there was no course limits other than leaving 3 capes to port, Good Hope, Leeuwin and Horn.  3 boats capsized deep in the Indian Ocean 
(Bullimore, Dubios, Dinelli) and one, Gerry Roufs, disappeared.   After this race although many competitors disagreed ice gates were introduced for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view (and I am allowed one as it is my blog) is that the ice wall is a necessary course container to prevent the unthinkable happening. 
In 1996 when Roufs was lost at sea the Vendee was still cutting edge and quite niche with only 16 entries.  This race has  29 competitors in far 
more advanced expensive boats  they are almost certain to better the race record of last event and keeping them a little north of the ice zone and the biggest 
storms of the southern ocean is a small price to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this version of the race Alex Thomson is still extending his lead as they dive toward Gough Island and start to bring the bows round onto an easterly course.
At this mornings 0800UTC report he was 130nm ahead of the second place boat.  This is starting to again put him into the next weather system which could be more favourable. 
He is also likely to keep the current strong winds for longer pushing him even further ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday13-0800.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 13 0900UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 13 0800UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-deep-into-the-south.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-deep-into-the-south.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 14 - The war of attrition starts.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So far in this Vendee Globe there has been relatively few broken boats in the first two weeks.
A welcome hiatus that has changed for the worse today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last Vendee (2013) 4 yachts retired in the first week alone with 3 being dismasted and one suffering a cracked hull.
So far in this edition one has returned to port and restarted and one has not retired yet but is sailing back toward
Les Sables-d’Olonne with a broken masthead where they will retire.  There has been few incidents on the yachts as well
apart from a few crunched ribs and banged heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all changed yesterday when Bertrand de Broc on MACSF retired after diving on his hull to see what damage had
been caused in a collision off the Portuguese .  It is reported that a large delaminated piece of material was hanging from his
hull causing vibration and a noise so loud that he could still hear it through noise canceling headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also yesterday British Race favourite &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson’s&lt;/a&gt; luck ran out when he hit something in the
water that has destroyed his starboard foil. The scheds over the next few hours showed him lose a 50nm chunk of the lead he had ground out
over the past couple of days.  Currently he is retaining the lead. Just.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you that watched the video I posted the other day where Hugo Boss engineering director
Ross Daniel talked about the foils you may remember he suggested that the boat would lose only a small
percentage of speed if it lost its foils.  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/15/vendee-globe-its-not-what-the-forecast-said.html&quot;&gt;Its Not What the Forecast Said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that it still has the port one and it is expected that most of the sailing across the southern ocean will be on starboard tack.
But Don’t take my word for it, lets hear it from the horses mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WHmueg44Fis&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other yachting news Land Rover BAR have won the entire LV challenger series.  This, I think, means they take a point into the AC knockout
next year.  I will check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vendeeglobe/vendeeday14-1700.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 14 1700UTC&quot; title=&quot;Vendee Tracker day 14 1700UTC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tracking2016.vendeeglobe.org/hp5ip0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;©Vendee Globe 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-the-war-of-attrition-starts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-the-war-of-attrition-starts.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vendee Globe 2016 Day 10 - New reference time to the equator.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexthomsonracing.com/&quot;&gt;Alex Thomson&lt;/a&gt; aboard Hugo Boss set a new reference time to the Equator of 9 days 7 hours and 3 minutes.
This is a full 1 day 4 hours faster than the previous time set by Jean Le Cam who is currently racing aboard FINISTÈRE MER VENT.
Le Cam in this edition was not one of the favourites and is currently in 9th position still 120 miles north of the equator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the time to the equator is referred to as a reference time.  Researching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sailspeedrecords.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.sailspeedrecords.com/&lt;/a&gt;
it appears there is no record to the equator from the usual start line of Lizard Point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking of records, the current fastest time for the Vendee Globe is 78d 2h 16m 40s by François Gabart on Macif.  The current speeds and the forecast for the South Atlantic should put that record under serious pressure.
However, long way to go yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this video of Boss rattling along at quite some speed sent from Hugo Boss in the last 12 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FAlexThomsonRacing%2Fvideos%2F1583671901646856%2F&amp;amp;show_text=0&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-record-to-the-equator.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/update/vendeeglobe/2016/11/16/vendee-globe-record-to-the-equator.html</guid>
        
        <category>sailing</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
        <category>vendeeglobe</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
